<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Sports &#8211; Portfolio &amp; CV</title>
	<atom:link href="/category/sports/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link></link>
	<description>Portfolio Website</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 12:25:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.5.2</generator>
	<item>
		<title>NEPALI CRICKET: A JOURNEY OF PASSION AND PROMISE</title>
		<link>/nepali-cricket-a-journey-of-passion-and-promise/</link>
					<comments>/nepali-cricket-a-journey-of-passion-and-promise/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Aayush Pathak]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 21 Apr 2024 12:21:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Sports]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">/?p=1247</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the shadows of towering peaks and amidst the serene beauty of the Himalayan nation, Nepal, a lesser-known cricketing tale has been unfolding—one filled with passion, perseverance, and the dream of making a mark on the international stage. While cricket has long held sway in countries like India, England, and Australia, Nepal’s ascent in the [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the shadows of towering peaks and amidst the serene beauty of the Himalayan nation, Nepal, a lesser-known cricketing tale has been unfolding—one filled with passion, perseverance, and the dream of making a mark on the international stage. While cricket has long held sway in countries like India, England, and Australia, Nepal’s ascent in the cricketing world is a story that deserves recognition.</p>



<p>Cricket is the most popular sport in Nepal. It is played by many people throughout the country. The biggest cricketing achievement of the national cricket team was when the team reached the qualification tournament of 2014 ICC World T20 held in Bangladesh. Recently nepal has qualified for the asia’s biggest cricket tournment ACC ODI Asia cup 2023 where they will be playing with the mighty India and Pakistan cricket team.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/groupphoto.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-596"/></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">History</h3>



<p>In 1920s&nbsp;Cricket&nbsp;was introduced to Nepal for the first time by Lt.-Gen. Madan Shumsher JBR&nbsp;youngest son of Rana&nbsp;Prime Minister&nbsp;Maharaja Chandra Shumsher<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chandra_Shumsher_Jang_Bahadur_Rana">&nbsp;</a>Jang Bahadur Rana. But at the time, cricket was considered a “gentleman’s game” so was limited to the ruling&nbsp;Rana family&nbsp;members and some elites of Nepal. Though the game was kept within themselves and other members of the elite, the&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cricket_Association_of_Nepal">Cricket Association of Nepal</a>&nbsp;was formed in 1946 to promote cricket amongst the aristocracy.</p>



<p>After the introduction of democracy through the&nbsp;Revolution of 1951,&nbsp;cricket&nbsp;began to spread to the rest of the population. In 1961, in an effort to promote cricket to the whole of&nbsp;Nepal, the&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cricket_Association_of_Nepal">Cricket Association of Nepal</a>&nbsp;became part of the&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/National_Sports_Council_(Nepal)">National Sports Council</a>. Nevertheless, the National games tended to be limited to&nbsp;Kathmandu&nbsp;until the 1980s.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team1-2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-40"/></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">ICC and ACC Membership</h3>



<p>After Cricket began to expand and spread outside the kathmandu valley and Cricket Association of nepal was established, Nepal became Affiliate Member of the ICC in 1988. Later in 1996 Nepal was granted with the Associate Membership from ICC.</p>



<p>Nepal became an Associate member of the ACC in 1990.</p>



<p>Nepal’s national side played their first ever cricket match in the year 1996, in the&nbsp;ACC Trophy&nbsp;in&nbsp;Kuala Lumpur.&nbsp;Nepal&nbsp;finished fourth out of six teams in their first round group in this competition, beating&nbsp;Brunei&nbsp;and&nbsp;Japan.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/nep.png" alt="" class="wp-image-41"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/icc.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-42"/></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Cricket Board</h3>



<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cricket_Association_of_Nepal">Cricket Association of Nepal</a>&nbsp;is the official&nbsp;governing body&nbsp;of the sport of&nbsp;cricket&nbsp;in&nbsp;Nepal, formed in 1946.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/can.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-17"/></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Major Achievements:</h3>



<ul>
<li><strong>The Road to T20 World Cup</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>One of the most significant milestones was Nepal’s participation in the ICC T20 World Cup in 2014. This journey was a testament to the hard work, determination, and skill of the players. Despite not clinching the title, their spirited performance captured the hearts of cricket lovers worldwide.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Nepal Cricket Team ODI Status</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Nepal has an official One Day International (ODI) status as of 2018. They won second place in Division Two of the 2018 ICC World Cricket League to get to this position.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Qualified for ODI World cup Qualifier 2018,2023</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Nepal qualified for ODI world cup qualifier for the first time in 2018 and second time in 2023.Nepal couldn’t qualified for world cup but get the chance to play matches with full member teams(test playing team).</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Asia cup 2023</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>Nepal qualified for the Asia Cup for the second time since they first play their matches in1996. In 2001 nepal qualified for Asia cup for the first time but couldn’t participate because the tournment was cancelled due to political dispute between India and pakistan.in 2023 Nepal qualifed for Asia cup beating UAE in the home ground in Asian premier cup final held in TU international cricket ground, Kathmandu.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/abc-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-43"/></figure>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">Challenges and Hurdles</h3>



<p>However, Nepal’s cricketing journey hasn’t been without its fair share of challenges. Inadequate infrastructure, financial constraints, and administrative issues have posed roadblocks to the sport’s growth. Consistency on the international stage remains an ongoing challenge.</p>



<p>The official governing body of cricket in Nepal<strong>&nbsp;</strong>Cricket Association of Nepal (CAN) was suspended from 2016 to 13 October 2019 due to governmental interference, though allowed the national teams to continue playing in international competitions.. The ICC welcomed the elections of the board held in September 2019 and formally reinstated the board on a conditional basis on 14 October.</p>



<p>Although cricket was introduce in nepal couple of decade ago, nepal has not been able to build even a single international standard stadium. Nepal play their home match in TU internartional cricket ground. recently another ground ,upper mulpani ground was prepared to host its first ever international tournment. upper mulpani ground also host a ODI match against Oman and UAE in the same tournment.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">some other challenges</h4>



<ul>
<li>No proper domestic structure</li>



<li>Lack of Investment from government and private sector</li>



<li>weak management and many more….</li>
</ul>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Future in Nepal cricket</h4>



<p>Despite these challenges, Nepal’s cricketing future is filled with promise. The country boasts a pool of talented cricketers, improved facilities, and a growing cricketing culture. Their participation in ICC events keeps the dream of representing Nepal on the world stage alive.</p>



<p>Another good aspect of nepal cricket is their passionate cricket fans.<br>Nepalese cricket fans are an extraordinary force of unwavering passion and unity, transforming cricket into a cultural phenomenon in the Himalayan nation. They transcend ethnic, linguistic, and geographical boundaries, fervently supporting the national team with vibrant celebrations, infectious enthusiasm, and fanatical fan groups. Cricket matches in Nepal are more than just games; they’re national festivals that bring people together, fostering an unparalleled sense of unity and pride. These dedicated fans not only celebrate local heroes like Paras Khadka and Sandeep Lamichhane but also utilize social media to connect with fellow enthusiasts, making cricket an ever-present part of their lives. Through the highs and lows of their team’s journey, Nepalese cricket fans remain steadfast in their support, exemplifying their enduring devotion to the sport and its power to unify a diverse nation.</p>



<h4 class="wp-block-heading">Cricket as a Unifying Force:</h4>



<p>Cricket has transcended its role as a sport in Nepal. It has become a unifying force that bridges divides, bringing together people from diverse backgrounds under the banner of their national team. The sight of fans waving the Nepali flag and passionately supporting their team is a testament to this unity.</p>



<p>In conclusion, the journey of Nepali cricket is an inspiration to cricket lovers worldwide. From humble beginnings to international recognition, Nepal’s cricketing tale is one of passion, aspiration, and the enduring spirit of a nation. As the nation continues to overcome challenges and nurture its young talents, there is every reason to believe that Nepali cricket will continue to rise and make its mark on the global stage. The future is bright, and Nepal’s cricketing heroes are ready to script the next chapters in this remarkable journey.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">NEPALI CRICKET GALLERY’S</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team1-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-20"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team3.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-22"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team2-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-23"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team5.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-27"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team4.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-25"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/team6.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-26"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/nepali-cricket-4.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-28"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/wteam.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-29"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/img2-2.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-30"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/abc.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-31"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/wteam-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-37"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/b.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-33"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/c.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-34"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/a-1.webp" alt="" class="wp-image-38"/></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image"><img decoding="async" src="http://localhost/wordpress/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/d-1.jpg" alt="" class="wp-image-39"/></figure>



<p>Drag widget here</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>/nepali-cricket-a-journey-of-passion-and-promise/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
